"HMB, Magnesium, Omega-3, and Vitamin D Supplements
for Age-Related Muscle Loss"
Previously,
I've covered the evidence
surrounding supplementation
for older adults with protein
or amino acids like leucine.
What about a metabolite
of leucine
known as beta-hydroxy-
beta-methylbutyrate,
known as HMB?
Adding HMB
to an exercise regimen
fails across the board
to improve muscle mass,
muscle strength,
or physical performance
among older individuals,
and since everyone
should be exercising,
that pretty much
takes HMB off the table.
But there are circumstances
when you're laid up,
for example, recuperating
from a broken hip.
Researchers in Spain randomized
about 100 men and women
over the age of 65 in rehab
recovering from a hip fracture
to a nutritional supplement
with about 3 grams of HMB.
They suffered less loss
of fat-free mass
compared to the control group
who didn't get the supplement.
Unfortunately, the supplement
provided other components,
so it's impossible
to tease out the HMB effects,
but regardless,
there was no significant change
in muscle strength
or muscle function.
This was roughly consistent
with a 10-day bedrest study
of straight HMB versus placebo
in which the HMB group
similarly lost less lean mass-
but only when an outlier
was excluded,
which isn't really kosher-
and there was
no apparent improvement
in strength or function.
This is what meta-analyses
of all such studies have found-
an improvement in fat-free mass
in older sedentary adults
with no change
in strength or function
and no benefits
for any muscle parameters
when combined
with physical activity.
Since we all should be
exercising,
and there's a questionable
benefit of lean mass
for lean mass's sake,
combined with the fact
that HMB activates
the engine-of-aging
enzyme mTOR,
I see little reason
to recommend
supplementing with HMB.
What about magnesium?
Higher blood levels correlate
with muscle performance.
And one cohort study
of older adults
found that those
with higher magnesium intake
had greater lean mass
over time,
though the dietary intake
of magnesium
appeared to be similar
between those
with and without sarcopenia,
excessive age-related
muscle loss.
There was one
randomized controlled trial
of magnesium supplements
that found that those taking
about the RDA for 12 weeks
had no effect on lean mass
or upper or lower body strength,
but it did appear
to improve walking speed
and chair to stand times.
Unfortunately, it wasn't
a randomized
placebo-controlled trial,
so that may all have just been
the placebo effect.
What about omega-3
fatty acid supplements?
Some population studies suggest
that fish consumption
is associated
with greater muscle strength.
In others, seafood consumption
was associated
with a greater loss
of muscle strength over time,
maybe because of
its mercury content.
When put to the test
in placebo-controlled trials,
fish oil and other
omega-3 supplements
showed no effect on lean mass,
or muscle strength,
or clinically significant
effects
on functional performance.
What about vitamin D?
Osteomalacia and rickets,
softened bone diseases
resulting from severe
vitamin D deficiency,
are often accompanied
by muscle weakness.
Mice genetically engineered
without vitamin D receptors
suffer muscle atrophy,
and vitamin D-depleted rats
show impaired muscle function.
In a Petri dish, vitamin D
increased muscle fiber growth.
Human observational studies
show correlations
between lower
vitamin D blood levels
and lower muscle mass,
lower muscle strength,
and performance
such as walking speed,
and higher odds of prefrailty
or frailty.
Of course, rather than
low vitamin D levels
leading to frailty,
frailty may be leading
to low levels
of the sunshine vitamin,
because frail individuals
may not be out
walking around as much.
You don't know
until you put it to the test.
Multiple meta-analyses
of randomized controlled trials
found that giving
vitamin D supplements to people
with low vitamin D levels
significantly improved
their muscle strength
and/or performance-
that is, until multiple studies
were retracted
for fabricated data.
It turns out, if you exclude
the fraudulent studies,
the benefit evaporates.
If anything, there may be
small adverse effects
to vitamin D supplementation
on muscle health.
The 180-degree turn
demonstrates
that the "publication
of fake data
can have
major health implications."